A Finding Aid to the Belisario Contreras Papers, 1943-1984, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Belisario Contreras papers
1943-1984
Archives of American Art
Contreras, Belisario R., 1916-
AAA.contbeli
Archival Resource Key
0.5 Linear feet
The papers of art historian Belisario Contreras measure 0.5 linear feet and date from 1943 to 1984. The papers document his research on New Deal Art Projects, including correspondence and copies of correspondence with William C. Agee, George Biddle (including 16 photographs of murals in Mexico City and Washington, D.C. and a clipping), Mrs. Edward Bruce, Olin Dows, Maria Ealand, Arlene Jacobowitz, Masha Zakheim Jewett (including an exhibition catalog and clippings on Bernard Baruch Zakheim), Horace Kallen, Rockwell Kent, Chet LaMore, Merwin C. Phelps, David W. Scott, Harold Weston, and others. Also found are National Endowment for the Humanities grant proposals "NDA Projects in Pennsylvania," 1975, and "Images of the Heartland," 1980, and notes from Contreras' interviews with Maria Ealand, John Gernand, Jacob Kainen, Dorothy Miller, and Selma Rein.
Biographical / Historical
Belisario Contreras was an Argentinian born art historian who lived and worked in Albuquerque, New Mexico. In 1983 he published the book "Tradition and Innovation in New Deal Art."
Scope and Contents
The papers of art historian Belisario Contreras measure 0.5 linear feet and date from 1943 to 1984. The papers contain his research on New Deal Art Projects, including correspondence and copies of correspondence with William C. Agee, George Biddle (including 16 photographs of murals in Mexico City and Washington, D.C. and a clipping), Mrs. Edward Bruce, Olin Dows, Maria Ealand, Arlene Jacobowitz, Masha Zakheim Jewett (including an exhibition catalog and clippings on Bernard Baruch Zakheim), Horace Kallen, Rockwell Kent, Chet LaMore, Merwin C. Phelps, David W. Scott, Harold Weston, and others; National Endowment for the Humanities grant proposals "NDA Projects in Pennsylvania," 1975, and "Images of the Heartland," 1980, and notes from Contreras' interviews with Maria Ealand, John Gernand, Jacob Kainen, Dorothy Miller, and Selma Rein.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research. Access to original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. Research Center.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated 1985 by Belisario Contreras.
Related Materials
Papers of Belisario R. Contreras, 1860-1976, are also located at The University of New Mexico's Center for Southwest Research.
Existence and Location of Copies
Portions of the collection are available on 35mm microfilm reel 3591 and 41 at Archives of American Art offices and through interlibrary loan. Researchers should note that the arrangement of material described in the container inventory does not reflect the arrangement of the collection on microfilm.
Latino and Latin American artists; Interviews; Art historians -- New Mexico -- Albuquerque; Zakheim, Bernard Baruch, 1898-1985; Bruce, Margaret T.; Dows, Olin, 1904-1981; Ealand, Maria; Gernand, John, 1913-1990; Jacobowitz, Arlene; Jewett, Masha Zakheim, 1931-; Kainen, Jacob; Kallen, Horace Meyer, 1882-1974; Kent, Rockwell, 1882-1971; La More, Chet Harmon, 1908-1980; Miller, Dorothy Canning, 1904-2003; Phelps, Merwin C.; Rein, Selma; Scott, David W., 1916-; Weston, Harold, 1894-1972; Agee, William C.; Biddle, George, 1885-1973; Federal Art Project
- AAA.contbeli holdings, Archival Resource Key
  - AAA - microfilm ILL- no restrictions, Archival Resource Key (Reel 0041.contreras)
  - AAA - microfilm ILL- no restrictions, Archival Resource Key (Reel 3591.contreras)
- Belisario Contreras Papers, 1943-1984; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 0.5 Linear feet Box 1, OV 2
  Scope and Contents
  The papers of art historian Belisario Contreras measure 0.5 linear feet and date from 1943 to 1984. The papers include his research on New Deal Art Projects, including correspondence and copies of correspondence with William C. Agee, George Biddle (including 16 photographs of murals in Mexico City and Washington, D.C. and a clipping), Mrs. Edward Bruce, Olin Dows, Maria Ealand, Arlene Jacobowitz, Masha Zakheim Jewett (including an exhibition catalog and clippings on Bernard Baruch Zakheim), Horace Kallen, Rockwell Kent, Chet LaMore, Merwin C. Phelps, David W. Scott, Harold Weston, and others; National Endowment for the Humanities grant proposals "NDA Projects in Pennsylvania," 1975, and "Images of the Heartland," 1980, and notes from Contreras' interviews with Maria Ealand, John Gernand, Jacob Kainen, Dorothy Miller, and Selma Rein.
  - William Agee, 1965-1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - George Biddle, circa 1958-1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - George Biddle, 1943 March 14; Archival Resource Key (Oversize 2)
  - Mrs. Edward Bruce, 1965-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Olin Dows, 1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Maria Ealand, 1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Arlene Jacabowitz, 1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Masha Zakheim Jewett, circa 1974-1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - President Lyndon Johnson, 1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Horace M. Kallen, 1965-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Rockwell Kent, 1964-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Jane Mathews, 1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Richard McKinzie, circa 1967-1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Dorothy Miller, 1964-1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Gerald M. Monroe, 1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Merwin c. Phelps, 1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - David W. Scott, 1965-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Archives of American Art, 1965-1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Columbia University, 1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - National Endowment for the Humanities Grant Proposals, 1975-1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Interviews with M. Ealand, J. Gernand, J. Kaimen, D. Miller, and S. Rein, 1964-1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Miscellaneous, 1964-1984; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 21)